A Finding Aid to the Silvia Pizitz Papers, 1927-1989, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Silvia Pizitz papers
1927-1989
Archives of American Art
Pizitz, Silvia
AAA.pizisilv
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of New York art collector Silvia Pizitz (1905-1991) date from 1927 to 1989 and measure 1.0 linear feet. Found are artist files, biographical material, correspondence, photographs and slides, and printed material. Of note are records concerning the donation of Pizitz's art collection and material relating to Pizitz's family department store in Birmingham, Alabama.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York art collector Silvia Pizitz (1905-1991) date from 1927 to 1989 and measure 1.0 linear feet. Found are artist files, biographical material, correspondence, photographs and slides, and printed material. Of note are records concerning the donation of Pizitz's art collection and material relating to Pizitz's family department store in Birmingham, Alabama.
Biographical / Historical
Art collector Silvia Pizitz (1905-1991) was active in New York City, New York. Born in Birmingham, Alabama, Pizitz studied at the Grand Central School of Art and continued her appreciation of art by acquiring a large art collection. Later in life, she donated her collection to various institutions including Cornell University, New York University, and the University of Birmingham.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 2006 by Raeford Liles, Pizitz's widower.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Collectors -- New York (State) -- New York
- Silvia Pizitz Papers, 1927-1989; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Artist files are found for Alice Barber, George Chemeche, and Dorothy Gillespie. Files contain photographs, scattered letters, and printed material. Biographical materials include biographical notes, identification cards for art schools, travel papers, and four small date books from the 1980s. Correspondence is with friends and family including writer Joseph Freeman, her siblings, and father Louis Pizitz. Many of the letters concern Silvia Pizitz's strained relationship with her family regarding inheritance and ownership of Pizitz department stores in Alabama. Records on the donation of her art collection to Cornell University, New York University, the University of Birmingham and other institutions include correspondence, appraisals, deeds of gift, and shipping records.
  Personal photographs include snapshots and portraits of Pizitz, Pizitz with friends and family, and travel. Photographs, negatives, and slides of works of art are by others, and are presumably pr items from Pizitz's collection. Some photos are of works by Raeford Liles. Of note are photos from an exhibition at the Birmingham Museum of Art of the Silvia Pizitz Collection. Printed materials include clippings and exhibition announcements, many of which concern the Pizitz family and her art collection. Also found are commemorative materials produced for or by the Pizitz department store to celebrate milestones and accomplishments.
  - Artist File, Alice Barber, 1976-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artist File, George Chemeche, 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Artist File, Dorothy Gillespie, 1978-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Material, 1927-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, circa 1927-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, circa 1927-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, circa 1927-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Donation of Art Collection, 1968-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Photographs, Personal, 1969-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, Exhibition, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Works of Art, circa 1970s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Printed Material, circa 1960-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Printed Material, Pizitz Department Store, 1952-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Slides and Negatives, circa 1960s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)